howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
this is a current episode currents are
shorter and less heavily produced than
our full-length episodes and generally
focus
on a single topic as always links to
books
articles and organizations mentioned are
available on the episode page at
gymrutshow.com that's jimrutshow.com
on today's current episode our guest is
steve levine
steve is editor at large at medium
writing on the impact of technology
science economics and demography
on jobs society politics and geopolitics
prior to medium he was editor for the
future at axios
steve is also a senior fellow from the
atlantic council's foresight
strategy and risks initiative and is an
adjunct professor
at georgetown university where he
teaches energy security in the graduate
level
security studies program steve's also
been on the show before where we did a
really excellent
episode about battery technologies if
you're interested in
climate change and uh renewable energy
check that episode out jim rudd shows
steve levine you'll find it
uh anyway today's current episode is
based on a medium post which i happen to
catch uh titled remote working is
killing the hidden trillion dollar
office economy uh steve
welcome hey jim tell me what you're
trying to get at with that essay
um so this is something that
it's a big thing that's hiding in plain
sight
and and that's that we know of course
that very few of us
are going to work um uh
office buildings those uh enormous uh
uh dense areas of our big cities
are ghost towns but uh
uh though a lot of those people
the white-collar folks who are working
in those big
buildings have kept their jobs they're
they're they're just home
working but but what they are they're a
uh the core of a much larger ecosystem
of of uh of suppliers for the buildings
uh uh mom and pop shops that surround
uh or or or are built within
uh these uh uh concentrated
areas and when you add all those
businesses
up you come to about uh a hundred
million
workers and so that and so that when
when we're talking about remote
uh you know perhaps the permanence of
remote
work or the semi permanence or only half
of us going back
we're talking about a tremendous blow
to a a very very large part of the us
economy
yeah indeed and those who listen to some
of my earlier podcasts on
uh covid related topics know that we
often frame the discussion
uh in complex systems terms when we talk
about hysteresis
and homeostasis which which are two
terms we use
that when a system receives a shock
homeostasis
means the tendency for it to return to
its previous state to essentially buffer
the shock
and things get back to normal may take a
while hysteresis on the other hand is a
term originally from physics
physics that when a shock to a complex
system is of sufficient magnitude
it never comes back and when i'm
thinking about these kinds of
uh effects around the pandemic uh you
know i like to
think about hysteresis what are
homeostasis which things will come back
and hysteresis which things will never
come back or at least will never come
back totally they'll go on a new
trajectory
uh and uh you know if i were to put down
a bet i put down at least a small one
that with respect to
uh you know traditional high dollar
big city office space uh we're talking
hysteresis
at least as much as homeostasis i kind
of doubt it's going to come back what
are your thoughts on that
you know when you're in the when you're
in the middle of the shock
then uh i i think that you're you're not
silly and it's hard to
to have a sensible uh
uh balanced appreciation
of what of what of what the long-term
impacts are going to be like
like in in sure you can think will this
ever end
is this ever going to end and things
things seem like and if
if history is an example uh prior
pandemics 1918
we did go straight into the roaring 20s
um and and so you know uh
that's that's um that's an
antecedent we have to look at but
what we're seeing now is is that time is
not standing
still so companies are taking stock
of how um how their
businesses have gone during this period
they've made
uh uh adjustments using zoom and other
uh video conferencing um uh
systems and um
you know so my own my own company medium
just announced last friday we're not
going back to the office
uh at least until this time next year
one more year
like this and uh and and so i have to
wonder if the
uh the uh hysteresis
thesis uh uh at least to some degree
is appropriate here simply because
companies see an upside in uh in
in embracing home from work indeed
and i think the other thing uh that's
really important to think about when
we're considering these questions
as compared to 1918 uh the
technical substrate really does make a
big difference
you know in 1918 there weren't really
any choices other than
uh going back to the office uh today
uh with you know things like the
internet and zoom
and lots of interesting and cool other
technologies that are just about to
emerge like
vr conferencing etc uh there's an
alternative and in fact uh
i've been arguing for some time that
business travel was stuck
in a sticky uh global sub-optima there
was really no reason for as much
business travel as we've had at least
since
maybe 2010 or 11 when uh
inexpensive or nearly free uh video
conferencing came out and reliable
video conferencing came on the scene but
you know there's habit and there's also
uh signaling right i'm not showing you
the proper
respect and deference if i don't travel
out to california to sit down with you
to
sell you a five million dollar software
package uh
when uh the shock to the system comes it
gave an excuse for people to get out of
that sub-optima or instead of spending
you know three days and two thousand
dollars to make uh
two sales calls uh one could make uh
20 sales calls in the same amount of
time
and so the being knocked out of that
basin of attraction
uh essentially allowed us to escape the
previous stickiness
uh that i believe a lot of it was around
uh you know signaling social signaling
of
uh people's relative importance and such
and
those may have the makings uh you know
of hysteresis because it's not really in
anybody's interest
uh i'd much rather talk to some sales
guy over zoom than have his uh
sweaty and greasy self in my office
right and as the sales guy himself
uh he could be way more efficient uh if
he doesn't have to
be traveling around the country so you
know i think that
uh kind of cultural inertia kept us in
some of these uh
basins and the shock allowed the marble
to fly out of the bowl
yeah this is jim such an interesting
point
this use your your use of this term uh
social signaling because
this is absolutely a key uh
a key factor in this in terms of
business travel
if you were in in an important meeting
uh sitting with you know the ceo
and the and the ceo and and uh
uh whomever else and uh
you had flown out to phoenix so you were
sitting with them
uh but the other guy is on the
is on the video right he's on the video
call
he's up there on this on the screen that
guy
on the screen he's got a delay right he
uh
uh you know it's very awkward to butt in
and you were a second class citizen you
you were not
if you wanted to be in uh to be really
in on decision making you more or less
had to be there but
kovid has turned everyone
no matter where they are into equal
uh equal citizens in that in that
meeting and uh that
that's likely to uh you know to to
linger
when this is all over indeed and the
other thing that's interesting
and it's become very clear because i do
probably uh
10 to 15 zooms a week in addition to
two or three podcasts a week or usually
two but sometimes more
i've noticed people are getting better
at it right and so there's
uh adaptation and social learning around
how to use these tools
uh and again that's uh you know kind of
trajectory dependent
uh evolution you know if we hadn't had
covid uh
the thing you described effectively i
can still recall uh
really hating to be on board meetings
remotely right because you were so
ineffective compared to being there
uh in person right and i would just
frankly just
say no i'm not gonna come on the zoom
i'll come in on the audio and just
listen and uh
you know play othello or something while
the meeting was going on
right uh but now we've all gotten way
better at it so again that uh
reinforces the trajectory it's cheaper
and we've gotten good enough
in general and cheaper is important you
know
one area that i'm quite involved in is
science governance and
facilitation of science and of course i
still do some scientific research myself
from time to time
and scientific meetings virtually are
amazingly
less expensive than
face-to-face in fact i just agreed to
fund three scientific meetings
and the costs are literally a tenth of
what they would be
if this if these had been uh
face-to-face meetings so that
uh you know the ability to have more uh
scientific meetings is
is actually uh very substantially
upregulated by this
uh systems dynamics uh change of going
to virtual
on the other hand there is some
downsides and you know i uh talk to
people especially younger people who uh
really
miss the opportunity for doing the
networking and the you know the
the famous statement that ah the
sessions aren't that important it's the
conversations of coffee that really
matter
so at least so far uh we haven't evolved
the virtual to be
to capture all the value of face-to-face
but we're doing it
at a tenth the cost let's say and i
suspect because we are
adaptive and learning animals uh our
tools
in the say in the next year you know if
medium is a good uh benchmark of how
long
uh there'll be a strong commitment to
this work at home and i suspect it's not
far off uh
we'll get these tools and we'll have the
equivalent of the uh
coffee conversations at scientific
meetings and uh and other kinds of
conferences
yeah that that that's a that's uh that's
the serendipity
factor you so so a a counter factual on
this
would be uh facebook is
snapping up real estate
uh you know in in silicon valley but
around the country it's
cheap now you know play uh with uh folks
going out of business
and so on why are they doing that why
facebook has announced that
that by 2030 uh it expects
half uh only half of its workforce to
have
returned to the office if that's the
case
why are they snapping up this real
estate and and
that that that factor that that
serendipity factor
that the young uh scientists
are are describing to you i think this
technology
is not is not there yet um it's
it's i i get um emails and and
uh you know pings from um
technologists with some frequency
claiming
that they've solved for serendipity you
know take a look at my
technology um but no one thinks so i
mean the
the folks who are actually using it
don't think that it's the same thing as
bumping it you know creating a virtual
room
at a conference where you know you can
enter it
and everyone else is in there it i mean
it it seems like it should be
um serendipitous but somehow
when you're in there it doesn't meet it
doesn't meet the same
uh uh the same bar and
maybe because you don't have a beer in
your hand while you're there i i'm not
sure
yeah i think you're right i've looked at
some of these too people are always
pitching me on these things and
i've yet to see one that actually does
it for me
however i am seeing improvement uh some
of the stuff originally was just
laughable but i'd say it's now
within striking distance uh and the one
i'm the area i'm most interested in
uh is vr conferencing that could
do it uh and i've heard for instance
that the vr
version of uh what's that damn thing
they do out in the desert burning man
uh is right apparently quite impressive
i've heard this from
multiple people i haven't had the uh
chance to or didn't get the chance to
engage with it uh but uh you know that's
just the kind of cutting edge thing well
there'll be some cultural learning
and uh we might get we might get some
serendipity out the other side that will
be uh be something very
interesting to watch over the next year
let's pivot now to the real estate
market i had not heard that
facebook was buying up real estate that
seems to me
i wouldn't be doing it unless the prices
were really cheap but which they might
be
you know buying assets at distress is
seldom a bad idea
but before our call i did a little
research and uh the number that i found
is that the
value last year i.e before the pandemic
of our all the office space in the
united states was 2.5
trillion dollars that's a damn big part
of the economy
right right and if you assumed a
possible contraction of maybe 50
in the value which doesn't strike me as
crazy because remember
uh in uh market capitalism everything
happens at the margin right and
uh marginal changes way less than fifty
percent can produce a fifty percent
decline in value yes you know think of
the fact that the stock market
goes down 50 from time to time and
that's probably only a 10
change in aggregate demand for stocks
anyway a 50 percent
contraction in the office market asset
value would be a bigger shock to the
financial system
uh than the uh mortgage crisis of 20
2008 and so and which triggered the
great recession so
uh it's it's worth con thinking about
the fact that
uh there's going to be some potential
financial follow-on if indeed there is
a long-term or even a short-term
diminishing in the value of
uh office space as an asset class
yeah i i i totally agree that um
so you're in a situation where um
uh already if um
companies are in distress um
and uh and not just companies because
when we're talking about the office
economy we're also talking about
retail restaurants uh um
shop shops like shoe shine uh
dry cleaners the the uh cleaners
the the uh you know the the list
of occupations that are reliant
uh on that office economy is
very very long and and and the part of
it that's just the white-collar workers
is not the majority and uh and and so
uh it's uh it's um you know when you
talk about the office
if if they're in distress and they can't
pay their
mortgage then the then the guy
who owns that office building he's got
to pay off the bank
uh too and and so yes
you you have a potential uh gut punch
to commercial real estate and to banking
this is a uh is a it is a
a a very uh worrying situation
economically and under appreciated the
scale of it
exactly and in fact the trend over the
last 10 years
20 years uh has been for most companies
to sell their office buildings and then
lease them back right and so the
purchasers have been financial
purchasers typically pretty highly
leveraged you know
80 90 percent debt uh finance
and so if you see a you know 40 50
decline in asset value the banks are
gonna have to call the loans
uh the asset holders are going to have
no way to repay the loans and it will be
a
cascading domino and the banks will then
seize the buildings put them back on the
market
at low prices trying to get what they
can get and that will accelerate the
downward trend in value which will cause
more
uh you know office building mortgage
holders to fail
so one could see a uh quite explosive
exponential
uh financial crisis evolving from this
uh
if it becomes clear that uh the demand
for office space is on a long term
uh decline right and and and then uh jim
i i'm wondering i haven't looked into
this maybe you have
but if not we could talk about it i i'm
certain
that uh office loans too
have have been uh have have been uh
turned into um uh
bonds right that that have been sold
and and you know the same you know that
uh
amplifying impact of of of you know of
uh uh you know cutting those into pieces
re reconstructing them into a an
allegedly
triple a loan and they spread around the
world yeah i would assume so i don't
actually know it's a good question i may
do a little bit of research on that
uh let's move on to another related
topic
i was talking to a economics professor
out at stanford
a couple weeks ago and he was confirming
what i had heard anecdotally
that there is a very sudden
uh very substantial exodus of people
from the big cities
uh you know san francisco new york uh
la for sure and probably a bunch of
others
and this could be an even greater uh
phase transition than the uh you know
retreat from
uh you know a class downtown office
buildings and
uh silicon valley uh if people just move
out of the cities entirely and move back
to where maybe life is better and a hell
of a lot cheaper
yeah this is now jim this can go both
ways right so so yes
you do end up and we are seeing that um
that folks who who who could barely
afford to live
in san francisco in new york um
are finding because of covid
that they can leave or they have to
leave and you know they just
they aren't employed anymore and that's
caused
rents to drop the last time i looked
which was a month ago
new york rents had dropped by six
percent
that's right it doesn't sound like much
but it's a lot right for a place like
new york um and
and and and so yes you do get this
exodus the but the other side of of that
is is and i i i hope that i'm not
upstaging
a um a section you wanted to lead to and
if so just tell me and we can
pause and then talk about it later but
you uh
you can end up you know you uh
the the uh the cost structure drops
one or two levels and then suddenly it's
affordable
for a new class of people and you
rejuvenate these cities
at a at a a at a stepped
lower lower cost of living yep and that
certainly will happen that
i mean that you know nothing is uh
linear everything is uh
non-linear systems with feedback loops
so certainly
let's say because rents have been going
down in new york for several years which
is interesting they've been going down
five or six percent for several at the
high end especially the you know three
thousand dollar one bedrooms and what
have you they've been uh coming down
for a while interestingly uh and
six percent is probably only a little
faster than they were coming down but
you're right yeah certainly it's gonna
be uh you know
then an opening up of opportunity and
uh you know one of the things that's uh
new york in particular is
horrendous for restaurant tours because
the rents are so damn high
uh you know if commercial real estate
rents fall on their ass it'll actually
open up a lot of opportunity for
restaurants that couldn't have existed
so it's never just one part of the
effect there's always a feedback loop
on the other hand if we talk about
hysteresis and homeostasis
uh you know people get lived in new york
or live in san francisco or silicon
valley l.a
because they felt they had to i suspect
an awful lot of them to pursue their
careers
uh and again as just like business
travel
it's actually been technically feasible
to do a lot of work
uh living in uh a much lower cost and
probably better quality of life place
uh for quite a while at least 10 years
but the pandemic
actually gave people the opportunity to
do it to try it
and the bosses wouldn't hold it against
them and i think it's at least
arguable that people will find that that
you know living in a rural area or a
small city
uh or even a medium-sized city uh you
know like pittsburgh
it's a very livable place very high
quality of life but the
you know cost of real estate's about
what is it maybe a fifth of what it
is in
new york or uh san francisco uh this
might be a permanent change it may well
be
that people particularly young people
who are the ones most beaten to ship
in the big cities uh because they don't
have the economic means you know four of
them living in a one-bedroom
apartment they may not no longer do that
anymore it may well make more sense to
live in a medium-sized city or even a
small city
and uh and make your living remotely
that'll be very interesting if that
happened
yeah yeah so you you've gotten me
thinking about
um what happened in in the black death
after the black death
the the other big um pandemic
and uh and it it uh
in the 14th and the 15th century one of
the things it did was
was lead to the um to the uh
uh disappearance of
the surf system and and uh and that
that that whole class divide uh
that that that that kept so much of the
european
population uh you know down
and uh you know with uh and all the
things we know
about that because uh you know
tragically
a third or a half of europe's population
died
then suddenly labor was at a premium
and so the the the survivors could uh
demand and did demand
much higher wages over uh decades and
decades of course
the folks the immediate survivors
didn't you know they they didn't achieve
any any uh upside that you know that's
what happens this time is that the folks
who lose their
their jobs the folks who lose their
businesses they're not the ones who are
going to
uh who are going to benefit from uh
you know a next uh positive stage
uh it'll be the next generation that
that
that that uh achieves that but
nevertheless
uh if if you uh just uh as
a thought experiment thought of an
analogy
to that of of uh of the creation
the elevation of a new middle class and
that you know it's thought that that's
what led
to the that that helped lead to the
reformation
and then the enlightenment and and and
all that was set up
for for the uh for the industrial
revolution uh you know you could think
here
so many people's uh living standards
have dropped people
a lot of people have fallen out of the
middle class over the last three
decades for you know for you know uh
all of the reasons that i'm i'm sure
you've discussed on the
on the show and uh and cities you're
ending up with
you know superstar cities superstar uh
professions if you're not in the
superstar professions
living in these super star cities then
you're stuck
at these lower living standards living
in uh
in in lesser communities
does this does does the step change
of covad 19 create
a new set of of uh of
costs uh and places to live
that that sort of open up
the gates for for uh uh for these folks
to to achieve the middle class status
that they no longer ha uh that they no
longer
had i think the answer to that is uh
probably yes in fact uh in our game b
movement uh which is a political social
change
uh not really political but uh social
change movement that i've been involved
with since the beginning
uh that's one of our uh visions is that
uh you know we were actually working on
it long before covet but that
a better way to live for a lot of people
particularly those not in the star
occupations it's a good uh way to
describe them
would be to live in rural areas or
outside small cities
uh where uh land is inexpensive but
quality of life is good
uh you know kind of on the model of the
israeli kibbutz i've done a fair amount
of research on
the kibbutz in fact had a scholar of the
kibbutz on the podcast recently
and we're actually starting to sketch
out some of these
uh settlements which we call proto-bees
is another version called
sivium also part of the game b movement
and the idea is they would be designed
to provide a
really good quality of living
for young couples with children
making maybe seventy thousand a year uh
between them so you know
uh that's seventy thousand dollars a
year uh say where i live in the
shenandoah valley of virginia
you're basically talking about an
assistant manager at wendy's
and a guy that works in a warehouse uh
for
uh walmart that would bring you up to
about seventy thousand dollars a year
uh he tried to live in new york city on
that kind of a income
and you'd be living in a you know rat
infested cockroach infested place way
out in one of the outer boroughs if
you're
lucky under our plan uh you could have
your own house with a lot of shared
infrastructure
extremely good quality of life an
excellent charter school system
associated with the community built in
daycare
etc which you could never possibly
afford in the uh
anywhere near any of the big cities yeah
so we're so we're painting
a a future that looks in the
in the short and medium term um
not so great especially for the folks
who who have lost their
businesses part of this office ecosystem
uh who won't they won't come back
they're not you know the
the guy who owned his own dry cleaners
mom-and-pop dry cleaners
or their their restaurant you know where
do they we don't know
where they go to but uh
but the next the next generation the the
folks who are coming into
who were just graduating college let's
say or just entering college
those those folks could uh
could end up uh benefiting
from from the uh from the the upheaval
caused by
kovitt yep that's you know kind of like
slash and burn agriculture right you
burn out the old and then something new
grows up yeah
and yeah and and and and the other thing
that we're i mean it's a it's a
it's a um it's an element that's just
sitting there and we've kind of
mentioned it i mean
but but just to bring it back in the the
cities them
the cities themselves can be can
uh can become much more affordable and
maybe not i i don't know maybe not
affordable for those folks
with a combined seventy thousand dollar
income but maybe a little bit more than
that
they can uh if they're young they can
move back they can move back to the city
yeah that would be interesting to see
how it goes i mean i'm not 100 sure the
big city is a humane place to live i
know a lot of people
like it uh but uh it strikes me as it's
quite alien from uh you know those
things which we actually resonate with
as human beings
uh you know beautiful nature uh you know
the ability to have
uh calm and quiet in one's life you know
safety for one's children
uh you know sense of knowing your
neighbors uh
real conviviality uh you know this
it's maybe an opportunity to escape that
whole urbanization thing that's going on
worldwide and that might
if that were to be the case uh that
would be the biggest outcome
uh from this shock yeah well okay so you
so you rate uh
so you raise um two things one
is the uh the consensus
forecast of uh of of of the big
uh uh white shoe think tanks
like uh like the boston consulting group
and mckinsey and all
you know uh uh bain that were
inexorably urbanizing
um this this this could
reverse that right yep that's a
hypothesis
uh and it uh probably doesn't do it
dramatically
right away but it may produce enough of
the you know the two percent innovators
to show the way
uh you know people are rightfully uh
skeptical about new ideas uh
particularly about how
how and where to live but you know let's
say two percent of people actually do
make the move over the next
ten years uh two percent six million
people that's a lot
right and if we have you know thousands
of small communities
on the order of a few hundred people who
are actually showing how
a really ultra wonderful way of life can
be had
at a quite reasonable uh level of income
uh that could then attract the next part
the so-called early adopters and you
know the next you know that when gen
z comes up and becomes ready to go out
into the workforce
uh maybe 15 percent of them uh move to
these
uh non-urban high quality of life
communities
and then over another couple generations
it becomes the norm and the city's
become depopulated of course this has
happened before i like to point out that
rome at its peak had a
population of i don't know a million and
a half something like that
uh by 800 a.d the population of rome
what was it
15 000. oh my god
15 000. uh so we have seen the decline
of cities in the past
and who knows maybe this is the
beginning of it you know it won't happen
overnight
it's going to be the work of generations
but truthfully my view
is that we'd be happier uh not living in
these giant urban
uh monsters that kind of squeeze the
humanity out
when i think of new york and i go to new
york used to go to new york fairly
regularly
the thing always strikes me in my mind
is sort of unhuman
is when you're riding the subway
everyone's looking down at their shoes
and not interacting with each other
and intentionally shutting each other
off it's just like a weird
weird weird way to live yeah
but but uh the uh
yes this is so and and that rome example
is so
dramatic urbanists
uh argue for your homeostasis
thesis on cities though they say cities
uh
have forever been forecast for death
uh but they bounced back and and
uh and rome did eventually bounce back i
don't know what what
what year did it come back to um to its
prior
uh level i guess it must have taken
hundreds of years
yeah i gotta graph somewhere with that
on it one of the presentations that i do
i don't have it
accessible at my fingertips and you're
right you know the two of the scholars
associated with our santa fe institute
uh jeffrey west and louise bettencourt
have done a lot of work on cities
and they point out that cities last way
longer than
companies or even countries right uh
you know damascus syria has been around
for some like
7 000 years through uh you know one
empire after the other one
conqueror after the other and damascus
is still there
so there's something about the form of
cities uh which
are very good for longevity but from
time to time they do disappear
and you know again uh the other thing to
keep in mind is that
we talked about the very beginning is
that the network
substrate may change everything uh
prior to inexpensive high quality uh
ability to interact via the network
there really wasn't a reasonable
alternative to the cities for
certain kinds of human collaboration
that may
no longer be true yeah that is right
so uh in in in uh in 1347
there was no zoom um as far as we know
as far as we know um but
it's interesting it's it's interesting
uh it's an interesting point but but but
uh
just from a policy perspective um
it's it's uh we're going to have if uh
policy makers need to think about the
the
potential impact to the cities i mean
to to to to smaller places that's a
positive impact you don't have to do
anything except perhaps you know pave
the roads and
uh you know and and bring in more
internet but
but uh but for the cities uh
the uh the impact not just it doesn't
matter if if you're
uh you know a red state guy
and why should we do anything for the
blue state guys or the blue city guys
uh this is the it's at a scale that's
the economy it's the u.s economy
it's a hundred million people who are
who who are in that
who are in that city economy everyone is
going to be hurt
yeah and this transition is going to be
painful for an awful lot of human beings
and we also need to you know consider
the fact there could be some very
adverse
uh political social uh impacts from the
short-term
negative shock uh you know and i look
back ominously at you know 1922-19
in germany right where the middle class
was first decimated by hyperinflation
which wiped out most of their savings
and then the great depression
a lot of people lost their jobs and as
you said they just knocked out of the
middle class or even out of the upper
working class
and when such things occur people are
willing to try
what in retrospect we can see is just
crazy ass
and you know we're starting to see
it you know both the left and the right
uh in the united states are you know out
in the streets killing each other at low
numbers so far
but that could accelerate at any time so
uh i suspect that
uh you know this more extreme uh
absolutist politics that we're seeing on
both flanks
may actually be accelerated by uh
you know the people who are being
knocked out of the uh the middle class
or even the upper working class
yeah i love this uh this formulation
the uh the sort of standard that you've
established
for uh for the uh the possibility of
where
where we could go um on the extremes
and it would be called uh the uh crazy
ass
uh uh metric yes
exactly one uh one to ten or one to 100
where are you on this scale
well it's one there's a group of us that
meet weekly to discuss this
and uh and some of the top i won't name
their names
some names you would know uh and our
current thinking
is that you know we're about a 10 out of
100 but
we're at could well be close to a cusp
where it goes to 80 out of 100 which
basically means
uh civil war or uh or
an authoritarian crackdown and we're
probably only a
one wrong event
away from a phase change from 10 out of
crazy to 70 or 80 out of 100 crazy
uh and the fact that uh people on both
sides are so
amped up so living in bubble chambers
where
uh they interpret the world through a
lens of radical ideology
uh and where any you know a random
happenstance event
uh could be amplified uh and produce
this phase change as i think what we
we're we're really concerned about uh
and you know the coming election could
provide that opportunity
uh you know uh a single or very small
group that creates some outrage you
imagine the uh
the alt-right sets off a car bomb in the
middle of a black lives matter
demonstration you know well
well within the capability of you know
five guys who are you know former
military people
uh what would that do in terms of a uh
inflection point or suppose the uh
on the other side the you know the
demonstrators in portland actually burn
down the house of the chief of police
and the police respond with a police
riot what would that do
to inflate the situation so there's an
awful lot of
close at hand nodes that could take our
current
uh 10 out of 100 situation and move it
to a into a much bigger situation
yes jim i'm totally with you i'm totally
with you
you get uh charlottesville was right was
just a little thing
it it in a you know a relatively small
group but but the
the uh you know the butterfly effect the
impact of this
it's it's remained with us and then uh
i'm thinking about
the other day there was a report it was
it was just in the last two or three
days there was a report in the new york
times
in portland of of protesters
going into a blm post protesters going
into
white neighborhoods and demanding that
uh
that that uh people make a show
of support for uh for their for uh
for that cause and then running across
encountering a house
where there was an american flag and
uh and making you know a big noise in
front of this person's house
and uh and then quoted again this is the
times it's not a crazy
this is not crazy media uh uh saying you
know if
if we come back tomorrow and that flag
is still there we're going to burn down
your house
um that you know uh that sort
of thing uh could turn into what you're
describing right it's
it's a uh it it's a it's
such a volatile uh time
and uh i mean we i guess we've kind of
gone off the
we've we've we've kind of diverged but
it but
if if people were employed i mean maybe
it's not disconnected if people were
employed
um and there weren't covered
uh you know maybe we wouldn't you know
we wouldn't have a lot of this stuff in
the
in the streets right now yeah that was
exactly my point which is that as people
start
having reason to have alliance with the
status quo
i.e they have a decent job uh they can
pay their rent etc
then this kind of stuff uh gets you know
it
it's happened before and peter's out
over time but it's a degree people are
kicked out of the middle class and and
don't really see an alternative then
the extremes of the right and the left
uh start to make sense right
yeah and that i think that was really my
point yes uh so so i think that you know
hopefully hopefully we can de-escalate
from this craziness
uh but we may not be able to uh
and you probably all of us individually
should try to
uh not get sucked into the vortex of the
left or the extreme all right now i call
them by the way i have a new name for
them the infrareds and the ultraviolets
and we have the red and the blue and if
you go on the spectrum beyond red and
blue you get infrared on the red side
and ultraviolet
on the on the blue side so uh you know
try not to get sucked into the vortex so
the infrareds
or the ultra of violence yeah
just just but but just to uh
uh to throw another ano another wild
card
in there a a poll yesterday or the day
before
how many americans regardless of
of uh ideology are prepared to take
the first generation of vaccine that
comes out
less than 50 percent whether you're
democrat or
republican yeah this is the erosion of
our sense-making capability due to
uh social media and its unintended
consequences
you know how many americans have died
from the side effects of vaccines since
a hundred oh my god it's a hundred
and uh most of those were one bad case
of the swine flu vaccine
vaccines are remarkably safe
uh and uh you know this is insanity
essentially this
anti-vaxxer thing uh and uh
you know if it wasn't for the fact that
we were uh
you know connected by a network of
contagion i'd say
you know hail mary fellows let darwinism
work its magic
right but unfortunately when people
don't take vaccines it puts us all at
risk so
people don't be idiots when the vaccines
are out
you know make sure you do your due
diligence you know i'm not sure i'd
use these russian and chinese vaccines
which are already out
without adequate testing but if they've
gone through the
you know full three stages no shortcuts
of the fda vaccine process it would seem
to me uh
nutso uh you know not to take the
vaccine
yes i agree i agree
and and and and just to just to close
the loop on that
all the things we're we're describing
uh are uh are uh
you know the outcome the outflow of
um of covet right if if we get
get this under under control even short
of a vaccine right just get
get control of our health system um
that would resolve a lot of this
it would certainly help it would it
would not be gasoline on the fire i do
believe we had
i mean the country was going nuts before
covet uh but covet has been
gasoline poured on the fire yeah i think
with that
uh with that note i think we're going to
wrap it up we've kind of reached our
45-minute
time window for a uh current uh episode
i really want to thank you steve for uh
extraordinarily interesting conversation
jim it was so great and uh we uh let's
do it again
and um uh i mean we covered so
uh so many topics but uh
last time we talked about batteries
batteries are you know
back on the back on the radar screen
with
elon musk we should uh return to that
sometime
sounds good
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting music by tom
muller at modernspacemusic.com